<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en, ru"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://mary-lev.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://mary-lev.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en, ru"/><updated>2025-06-22T13:22:54+00:00</updated><id>https://mary-lev.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">TEI Encoding as a Unified Structure for Multilingual Digital Editions</title><link href="https://mary-lev.github.io/blog/2025/aiucd-tei-encoding/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="TEI Encoding as a Unified Structure for Multilingual Digital Editions"/><published>2025-06-11T09:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-06-11T09:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mary-lev.github.io/blog/2025/aiucd-tei-encoding</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mary-lev.github.io/blog/2025/aiucd-tei-encoding/"><![CDATA[<p>I presented the LeggoManzoni case study at AIUCD-2025 (The 14th Annual Conference of the Association of Digital Humanities and Digital Culture) in Verona, Italy. This presentation, co-authored with Beatrice Nava and Ersilia Russo, demonstrated how TEI encoding can serve as a unified structure for multilingual digital editions.</p> <h2 id="research-context">Research Context</h2> <p>The presentation addressed a key challenge in digital scholarly editing: how to create coherent, interoperable multilingual editions that maintain scholarly standards while enabling computational analysis and user interaction.</p> <h2 id="the-leggomanzoni-project">The LeggoManzoni Project</h2> <p>LeggoManzoni is a comprehensive digital edition project centered on Alessandro Manzoni’s “I Promessi Sposi” (The Betrothed), featuring:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Multiple language versions</strong>: Italian original and various translations</li> <li><strong>Critical apparatus</strong>: Scholarly annotations and commentary</li> <li><strong>Interactive features</strong>: Enhanced reading experience with digital tools</li> <li><strong>Educational focus</strong>: Resources for teaching Italian literature</li> </ul> <h2 id="tei-implementation-strategy">TEI Implementation Strategy</h2> <p>Our approach demonstrates how TEI encoding can:</p> <h3 id="unify-multiple-texts">Unify Multiple Texts</h3> <ul> <li><strong>Parallel structure</strong>: Consistent encoding across different language versions</li> <li><strong>Alignment markers</strong>: Linking corresponding passages between texts</li> <li><strong>Hierarchical organization</strong>: Maintaining textual relationships at multiple levels</li> </ul> <h3 id="support-multilingual-features">Support Multilingual Features</h3> <ul> <li><strong>Language identification</strong>: Proper markup for different languages and dialects</li> <li><strong>Translation relationships</strong>: Explicit connections between source and target texts</li> <li><strong>Cultural annotations</strong>: Context-sensitive explanatory materials</li> </ul> <h3 id="enable-computational-analysis">Enable Computational Analysis</h3> <ul> <li><strong>Structured data</strong>: Machine-readable format for text mining and analysis</li> <li><strong>Standardized markup</strong>: Interoperability with digital humanities tools</li> <li><strong>Extensible framework</strong>: Capacity for future enhancements and additions</li> </ul> <h2 id="technical-innovations">Technical Innovations</h2> <p>The project showcases several advances in TEI practice:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Modular design</strong>: Reusable components for different texts and languages</li> <li><strong>Validation frameworks</strong>: Quality assurance for complex multilingual markup</li> <li><strong>Publishing workflows</strong>: From TEI source to multiple output formats</li> </ul> <h2 id="broader-implications">Broader Implications</h2> <p>This work contributes to:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Digital edition methodology</strong>: Best practices for multilingual projects</li> <li><strong>TEI development</strong>: Extending standards for complex use cases</li> <li><strong>Cultural heritage</strong>: Preserving and presenting literary works digitally</li> <li><strong>Educational technology</strong>: Tools for literature teaching and learning</li> </ul> <h2 id="publication">Publication</h2> <p>The full paper is available with detailed technical specifications and case study analysis, providing a replicable model for similar multilingual digital edition projects.</p> <p>The LeggoManzoni project exemplifies how rigorous encoding standards can support both scholarly research and public engagement with literary heritage.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="conferences"/><category term="digital-editions"/><category term="TEI"/><category term="digital-editions"/><category term="multilingual-texts"/><category term="XML"/><category term="encoding"/><category term="LeggoManzoni"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[AIUCD-2025, Verona, Italy]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Subject Indexing, Chatbot, and Computational Text Analysis in Zemelah.online: A Digital Archive of Soviet-Era Jewish Egodocuments</title><link href="https://mary-lev.github.io/blog/2025/israeli-dh-zemelah-archive/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Subject Indexing, Chatbot, and Computational Text Analysis in Zemelah.online: A Digital Archive of Soviet-Era Jewish Egodocuments"/><published>2025-06-10T09:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-06-10T09:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mary-lev.github.io/blog/2025/israeli-dh-zemelah-archive</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mary-lev.github.io/blog/2025/israeli-dh-zemelah-archive/"><![CDATA[<p>I will be presenting my collaborative work with Anastasia Glazanova (The Central Archives for the History of the Jewish People) on the Zemelah.online digital archive at the Israeli International Conference on Digital Humanities and Social Sciences at The Open University of Israel in Ra’anana.</p> <h2 id="project-overview">Project Overview</h2> <p>Zemelah.online is a digital archive preserving and analyzing Soviet-era Jewish egodocuments. Our collection encompasses diverse material types: handwritten manuscripts, typewritten documents, and small-edition publications produced for family and friends. The project reveals diverse experiences that challenge conventional scholarly frameworks — from stories of victimhood to achievement, from acculturation to religious observance.</p> <h2 id="evolution-with-ai-technology">Evolution with AI Technology</h2> <p>Beginning in late 2020, the project has evolved significantly alongside rapid developments in Large Language Models since 2023:</p> <h3 id="initial-phase-2020-2023">Initial Phase (2020-2023)</h3> <ul> <li>Systematic document processing and qualitative text analysis</li> <li>Manual indexing of key entities (locations, persons, organizations)</li> <li>Thematic content indexing covering Jewish-specific and universal subjects</li> </ul> <h3 id="ai-integration-phase-2023-present">AI Integration Phase (2023-present)</h3> <ul> <li><strong>Markup editor</strong> with pre-annotation using Claude and fixed tag sets</li> <li><strong>GPT-powered chatbot</strong> enabling thematic queries and text fragment retrieval</li> <li><strong>Computational text analysis</strong> using multiple methodological approaches</li> </ul> <h2 id="computational-analysis-methods">Computational Analysis Methods</h2> <h3 id="topic-modeling-with-lda">Topic Modeling with LDA</h3> <p>Using Latent Dirichlet Allocation, we identified <strong>8 distinct thematic clusters</strong> in Soviet Jewish narratives:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Family/Childhood</strong> (20.96% - most prevalent theme)</li> <li><strong>Personal Correspondence</strong></li> <li><strong>Soviet Jewish Experience</strong></li> <li><strong>Military/Navy Life</strong></li> <li><strong>War/Holocaust narratives</strong></li> <li><strong>Professional/Medical narratives</strong></li> </ul> <h3 id="key-finding-narrative-separation">Key Finding: Narrative Separation</h3> <p>A statistically significant <strong>negative correlation (-0.32)</strong> between Family/Childhood narratives and Soviet Jewish Experience topics reveals a compelling narrative strategy: authors tend to separate intimate family memories from institutional/political experiences, creating distinct storytelling modes that reflect complex navigation of private and public spheres in Soviet Jewish life.</p> <h3 id="technical-implementation">Technical Implementation</h3> <ul> <li><strong>Russian-specific preprocessing</strong>: Modified stopword lists for memoir narratives</li> <li><strong>pymorphy2</strong> for Russian lemmatization</li> <li><strong>Optimal parameters</strong>: 8 topics with document-topic prior (alpha) of 0.1 and topic-word prior (beta) of 0.01</li> <li><strong>Cross-validation</strong> for empirical parameter determination</li> </ul> <h2 id="ongoing-research-directions">Ongoing Research Directions</h2> <ul> <li><strong>Sentiment analysis</strong> to map emotional patterns across the corpus</li> <li><strong>Word embeddings (word2vec)</strong> to visualize semantic networks</li> <li><strong>Multi-method correlation analysis</strong> examining how themes relate to emotional expression</li> </ul> <h2 id="research-impact">Research Impact</h2> <p>This project demonstrates how “ordinary” Soviet Jews documented their experiences, providing computational insights into:</p> <ul> <li>Narrative strategies in historical ego-documents</li> <li>Private vs. public sphere navigation in Soviet Jewish life</li> <li>Emotional and semantic patterns in memoir writing</li> <li>Digital preservation of cultural heritage materials</li> </ul> <h2 id="resources">Resources</h2> <ul> <li><strong>Code Repository</strong>: <a href="https://github.com/mary-lev/topic_modeling">GitHub</a></li> <li><strong>Project Website</strong>: Zemelah.online</li> </ul> <p><strong>Conference dates</strong>: June 10, 2025<br/> <strong>Location</strong>: Ra’anana, Israel<br/> <strong>Event</strong>: Israeli International Conference on Digital Humanities and Social Sciences 2025</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="conferences"/><category term="digital-archives"/><category term="digital-archives"/><category term="jewish-studies"/><category term="topic-modeling"/><category term="LDA"/><category term="sentiment-analysis"/><category term="chatbot"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Israeli International Conference on Digital Humanities and Social Sciences, Ra'anana, Israel]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">LeggoManzoni Workshop at Peking University: Digital Humanities Meets Chinese Translation</title><link href="https://mary-lev.github.io/blog/2025/leggomanzoni-workshop-peking-university/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="LeggoManzoni Workshop at Peking University: Digital Humanities Meets Chinese Translation"/><published>2025-03-20T09:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-20T09:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mary-lev.github.io/blog/2025/leggomanzoni-workshop-peking-university</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mary-lev.github.io/blog/2025/leggomanzoni-workshop-peking-university/"><![CDATA[<p>On March 20, 2025, the University of Bologna team led an innovative workshop at Peking University, introducing Chinese students to digital humanities methodologies through Alessandro Manzoni’s <em>I Promessi Sposi</em>. This international collaboration showcased how digital tools can bridge linguistic and cultural boundaries in literary studies.</p> <h2 id="workshop-structure">Workshop Structure</h2> <p>The session featured two complementary presentations that provided both literary-historical context and technical methodology:</p> <h3 id="literary-evolution-presentation">Literary Evolution Presentation</h3> <p><strong>Prof. Paola Italia</strong> discussed the fascinating evolution of Manzoni’s masterpiece from its original version <em>Fermo e Lucia</em> to the final <em>I Promessi Sposi</em>, providing students with crucial literary-historical background for understanding the text’s development and significance.</p> <h3 id="digital-methodology-presentation">Digital Methodology Presentation</h3> <p><strong>Mariia Levchenko</strong> presented the technical aspects of multilingual digital editions, focusing on the LeggoManzoni platform’s innovative pipeline for integrating multiple translations across different languages and historical periods.</p> <h2 id="hands-on-learning-experience">Hands-On Learning Experience</h2> <p>The workshop’s highlight was the practical XML/TEI markup session, where Chinese students learned to encode Zhang Shihua’s 1998 Chinese translation of <em>I Promessi Sposi</em>. This hands-on approach demonstrated:</p> <ul> <li><strong>TEI encoding principles</strong> applied to Chinese literary translation</li> <li><strong>Segment-level alignment technology</strong> enabling precise correlation between Italian source text and Chinese translation</li> <li><strong>Peer-to-peer learning</strong> as students collaborated on digital text encoding</li> <li><strong>Real contribution</strong> to the expanding TRADUCO MANZONI module</li> </ul> <h2 id="international-collaboration">International Collaboration</h2> <p>This workshop represents part of a broader international collaboration between the University of Bologna and Peking University, aimed at making Italian literature more accessible through innovative digital tools. The partnership demonstrates how digital humanities can:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Bridge cultural gaps</strong> through technological innovation</li> <li><strong>Facilitate cross-linguistic scholarly exchange</strong></li> <li><strong>Create reusable digital resources</strong> for future research and education</li> <li><strong>Train new generation</strong> of digital humanities practitioners globally</li> </ul> <h2 id="technical-innovation">Technical Innovation</h2> <p>The LeggoManzoni platform’s ability to handle Chinese text encoding showcased the versatility of TEI standards for multilingual digital editions. Students experienced firsthand how:</p> <ul> <li>Digital tools can preserve and present literary translations</li> <li>XML/TEI markup creates structured, searchable text corpora</li> <li>Alignment technology enables comparative literary analysis across languages</li> <li>International scholarly collaboration can be enhanced through shared digital infrastructure</li> </ul> <h2 id="impact-and-future-directions">Impact and Future Directions</h2> <p>This workshop marks an important milestone in international digital humanities education, demonstrating how collaborative projects can simultaneously advance scholarly research and cross-cultural understanding. The encoded Chinese translation will become part of the growing LeggoManzoni multilingual corpus, contributing to global accessibility of Italian literary heritage.</p> <p>The success of this workshop opens possibilities for further collaboration between Italian and Chinese institutions in digital humanities, potentially expanding to other literary works and creating sustainable models for international scholarly exchange in the digital age.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="workshops"/><category term="digital-humanities"/><category term="international-collaboration"/><category term="digital-humanities"/><category term="TEI-encoding"/><category term="multilingual-editions"/><category term="LeggoManzoni"/><category term="China"/><category term="international-collaboration"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[University of Bologna team leads innovative digital humanities workshop at Peking University]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Literary Communities in Saint Petersburg 1999-2019</title><link href="https://mary-lev.github.io/blog/2025/graphs-networks-literary-communities/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Literary Communities in Saint Petersburg 1999-2019"/><published>2025-02-13T09:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-13T09:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mary-lev.github.io/blog/2025/graphs-networks-literary-communities</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mary-lev.github.io/blog/2025/graphs-networks-literary-communities/"><![CDATA[<p>I presented my research on literary communities at the Graphs &amp; Networks Conference 2025 at Università della Svizzera italiana in Mendrisio, Switzerland. This presentation explored the application of graph theory and network analysis to understand literary community formation and evolution.</p> <h2 id="conference-context">Conference Context</h2> <p>The Graphs &amp; Networks Conference brings together researchers from various disciplines who apply network analysis methods to complex systems. This interdisciplinary venue was ideal for presenting literary network analysis to a broader scientific community.</p> <h2 id="research-overview">Research Overview</h2> <p>The study examined how literary communities in Saint Petersburg formed, evolved, and dissolved over a 20-year period (1999-2019) using graph-theoretic approaches applied to cultural data.</p> <h2 id="network-analysis-methods">Network Analysis Methods</h2> <p>The research employed several network analysis techniques:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Community detection algorithms</strong>: Identifying clusters of closely connected literary actors</li> <li><strong>Centrality measures</strong>: Determining influential nodes in the literary network</li> <li><strong>Temporal network analysis</strong>: Tracking changes in community structure over time</li> <li><strong>Homophily analysis</strong>: Examining how similar actors tend to connect</li> </ul> <h2 id="key-findings">Key Findings</h2> <p>The analysis revealed:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Distinct literary communities</strong>: Separate clusters based on genre, generation, and aesthetic preferences</li> <li><strong>Bridge figures</strong>: Individuals who connected different literary circles</li> <li><strong>Temporal dynamics</strong>: How communities merged, split, and reformed over time</li> <li><strong>Structural patterns</strong>: Common organizational principles in literary networks</li> </ul> <h2 id="methodological-innovation">Methodological Innovation</h2> <p>This work demonstrates how:</p> <ul> <li>Graph theory can illuminate cultural phenomena</li> <li>Literary data can be analyzed using network science methods</li> <li>Temporal analysis reveals community evolution patterns</li> <li>Interdisciplinary approaches enrich literary studies</li> </ul> <h2 id="broader-implications">Broader Implications</h2> <p>The research contributes to:</p> <ul> <li>Understanding cultural network dynamics</li> <li>Developing methods for analyzing literary communities</li> <li>Bridging humanities and network science</li> <li>Providing tools for cultural policy and literary history</li> </ul> <p>The work showcases how computational methods can offer new insights into traditional humanities questions while respecting the complexity of cultural phenomena.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="conferences"/><category term="network-analysis"/><category term="network-analysis"/><category term="literary-communities"/><category term="graph-theory"/><category term="Saint-Petersburg"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Graphs & Networks Conference 2025, Università della Svizzera italiana, Mendrisio, Switzerland]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">St. Petersburg Literary Network (based on the SPbLitGuide newsletters)</title><link href="https://mary-lev.github.io/blog/2025/dh-russia-spb-network/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="St. Petersburg Literary Network (based on the SPbLitGuide newsletters)"/><published>2025-01-31T09:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-31T09:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mary-lev.github.io/blog/2025/dh-russia-spb-network</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mary-lev.github.io/blog/2025/dh-russia-spb-network/"><![CDATA[<p>I presented my research on the St. Petersburg literary network at the DH-Russia National Research and Project Seminar “Digital Humanities Projects: Models, Problems, Prospects” in Moscow. This presentation focused on the social network analysis of literary communities based on data from SPbLitGuide newsletters.</p> <h2 id="research-background">Research Background</h2> <p>The SPbLitGuide newsletters documented literary events in Saint Petersburg from 1999 to 2019, providing a unique dataset for understanding the evolution of the city’s literary community over two decades.</p> <h2 id="network-analysis-approach">Network Analysis Approach</h2> <p>The research employed social network analysis techniques to:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Map literary connections</strong>: Identify relationships between authors, venues, and cultural institutions</li> <li><strong>Analyze community structure</strong>: Detect clusters and subgroups within the literary network</li> <li><strong>Track temporal evolution</strong>: Examine how the network changed over the 20-year period</li> <li><strong>Identify key actors</strong>: Determine influential figures and venues in the literary landscape</li> </ul> <h2 id="key-findings">Key Findings</h2> <p>The analysis revealed:</p> <ul> <li>Central venues that served as hubs for literary activity</li> <li>Distinct literary communities and their interconnections</li> <li>Temporal patterns in network formation and dissolution</li> <li>The role of specific events in connecting different literary circles</li> </ul> <h2 id="methodological-contributions">Methodological Contributions</h2> <p>This work demonstrates how digital humanities approaches can:</p> <ul> <li>Transform archival materials into structured data for analysis</li> <li>Apply network science methods to literary history</li> <li>Provide quantitative insights into cultural phenomena</li> <li>Support traditional literary scholarship with computational methods</li> </ul> <h2 id="data-availability">Data Availability</h2> <p>The underlying dataset is available on Zenodo: <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.10086515">Literary Events in Saint Petersburg (1999-2019)</a></p> <h2 id="impact">Impact</h2> <p>This research contributes to understanding Russian literary communities and demonstrates the potential of digital methods for cultural analysis, offering new perspectives on the social dynamics of literary production and distribution.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="conferences"/><category term="digital-humanities"/><category term="social-network-analysis"/><category term="russian-literature"/><category term="Saint-Petersburg"/><category term="digital-humanities"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[DH-Russia National Research and Project Seminar, Moscow, Russia]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Automatic Translation Alignment Pipeline for Multilingual Digital Editions of Literary Works</title><link href="https://mary-lev.github.io/blog/2024/chr2024-translation-pipeline/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Automatic Translation Alignment Pipeline for Multilingual Digital Editions of Literary Works"/><published>2024-12-04T09:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-04T09:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mary-lev.github.io/blog/2024/chr2024-translation-pipeline</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mary-lev.github.io/blog/2024/chr2024-translation-pipeline/"><![CDATA[<p>I presented my research on automatic translation alignment at the Computational Humanities Research Conference 2024 at Aarhus University in Denmark. This presentation detailed the development of an automated pipeline for aligning translations in multilingual digital editions.</p> <h2 id="research-overview">Research Overview</h2> <p>The project addresses a critical challenge in digital humanities: how to automatically align texts across multiple languages and editions to create comprehensive multilingual digital scholarly editions.</p> <h2 id="technical-approach">Technical Approach</h2> <p>The pipeline integrates several computational methods:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Text preprocessing</strong>: Normalization and segmentation of source and target texts</li> <li><strong>Alignment algorithms</strong>: Advanced techniques for identifying corresponding text segments</li> <li><strong>Quality assessment</strong>: Automated evaluation of alignment accuracy</li> <li><strong>TEI integration</strong>: Export of aligned texts in TEI-compliant XML format</li> </ul> <h2 id="case-study-i-promessi-sposi">Case Study: I Promessi Sposi</h2> <p>The methodology was tested on Alessandro Manzoni’s “I Promessi Sposi” and its translations, demonstrating:</p> <ul> <li>Effectiveness across different language pairs</li> <li>Handling of structural variations between editions</li> <li>Integration with existing digital edition frameworks</li> </ul> <h2 id="key-contributions">Key Contributions</h2> <ul> <li>Development of a robust automatic alignment pipeline</li> <li>Evaluation metrics for translation alignment quality</li> <li>Integration strategies for multilingual TEI documents</li> <li>Practical solutions for common alignment challenges</li> </ul> <h2 id="publication">Publication</h2> <p>The full paper is available in the CHR 2024 Proceedings: <a href="https://ceur-ws.org/Vol-3834/paper128.pdf">CEUR-WS Vol-3834, pp. 1086-1104</a></p> <h2 id="impact">Impact</h2> <p>This work contributes to making multilingual digital editions more accessible and scalable, reducing the manual effort required for creating aligned translations while maintaining scholarly standards for digital textual scholarship.</p> <p>The pipeline has been applied to the LeggoManzoni project and is being adapted for other multilingual digital edition projects.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="conferences"/><category term="computational-humanities"/><category term="translation-alignment"/><category term="computational-humanities"/><category term="multilingual-editions"/><category term="NLP"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Computational Humanities Research 2024, Aarhus University, Denmark]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">СтихиРу vs поэтический канон: к вопросу о количественном измерении графомании</title><link href="https://mary-lev.github.io/blog/2024/grafomaniya-conference/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="СтихиРу vs поэтический канон: к вопросу о количественном измерении графомании"/><published>2024-10-07T09:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-07T09:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mary-lev.github.io/blog/2024/grafomaniya-conference</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mary-lev.github.io/blog/2024/grafomaniya-conference/"><![CDATA[<p>I presented my research on quantitative approaches to analyzing Russian poetry at the conference “Графомания. Русская литература и ее границы” (Graphomania. Russian Literature and Its Boundaries) at the Institute of Russian Literature (Pushkinskij Dom) in Saint Petersburg.</p> <h2 id="research-question">Research Question</h2> <p>The presentation addressed the question of how computational methods can help distinguish between canonical poetry and what might be considered “graphomania” - examining whether quantitative measures can capture qualitative differences in literary value.</p> <h2 id="methodology">Methodology</h2> <p>The study compared texts from Стихи.ру (Stihi.ru), a popular Russian poetry platform, with established poetic canon using various computational metrics:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Linguistic features</strong>: Vocabulary diversity, syntactic complexity, rhythmic patterns</li> <li><strong>Statistical analysis</strong>: Frequency distributions, stylometric measures</li> <li><strong>Comparative analysis</strong>: Canonical vs. non-canonical poetry characteristics</li> </ul> <h2 id="key-findings">Key Findings</h2> <p>The research explored whether computational methods can identify markers that distinguish between:</p> <ul> <li>Canonical Russian poetry from the literary tradition</li> <li>Contemporary poetry published on digital platforms</li> <li>The boundaries and overlaps between these categories</li> </ul> <h2 id="theoretical-implications">Theoretical Implications</h2> <p>The presentation examined the broader theoretical questions around:</p> <ul> <li>Digital humanities approaches to literary value assessment</li> <li>The role of computational methods in literary criticism</li> <li>Challenges in defining and measuring literary quality</li> </ul> <h2 id="conference-context">Conference Context</h2> <p>This conference brought together scholars examining the boundaries of Russian literature, providing an important forum for discussing how digital methods can inform traditional literary studies while respecting the complexity of aesthetic judgment.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="conferences"/><category term="russian-literature"/><category term="russian-poetry"/><category term="computational-analysis"/><category term="literary-canon"/><category term="digital-humanities"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Графомания. Русская литература и ее границы, Institute of Russian Literature, Saint Petersburg]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Manual and Automatic Alignment of I Promessi Sposi: Results and Open Issues</title><link href="https://mary-lev.github.io/blog/2024/roma-translation-alignment/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Manual and Automatic Alignment of I Promessi Sposi: Results and Open Issues"/><published>2024-09-26T09:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-26T09:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mary-lev.github.io/blog/2024/roma-translation-alignment</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mary-lev.github.io/blog/2024/roma-translation-alignment/"><![CDATA[<p>I participated in the workshop “Aligned Translations for Digital Scholarly Editions: Methodologies, Methods, and Workflows” at the Istituto Italiano di Studi Germanici in Rome, presenting my work on the alignment challenges in multilingual digital editions.</p> <h2 id="presentation-focus">Presentation Focus</h2> <p>The presentation examined both manual and automatic approaches to aligning different versions and translations of Alessandro Manzoni’s “I Promessi Sposi” (The Betrothed), discussing the practical challenges and theoretical implications of creating aligned multilingual digital editions.</p> <h2 id="key-topics-covered">Key Topics Covered</h2> <ul> <li><strong>Manual alignment workflows</strong>: Traditional philological approaches adapted for digital environments</li> <li><strong>Automatic alignment pipelines</strong>: Computational methods for text alignment across languages and editions</li> <li><strong>Quality assessment</strong>: Comparing manual and automatic alignment results</li> <li><strong>Open challenges</strong>: Remaining issues in multilingual digital edition creation</li> </ul> <h2 id="technical-challenges">Technical Challenges</h2> <p>The work highlighted several persistent challenges in translation alignment:</p> <ul> <li>Handling different text structures across languages</li> <li>Managing varying levels of textual correspondence</li> <li>Balancing accuracy with processing efficiency</li> <li>Integrating alignment data into TEI-compliant formats</li> </ul> <h2 id="workshop-context">Workshop Context</h2> <p>This workshop brought together scholars working on multilingual digital editions, providing a valuable forum for discussing methodological approaches and sharing practical solutions for common challenges in the field.</p> <p>The research contributes to the broader LeggoManzoni project, which aims to create comprehensive multilingual digital editions with integrated critical apparatus.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="conferences"/><category term="digital-editions"/><category term="translation-alignment"/><category term="digital-editions"/><category term="TEI"/><category term="multilingual-texts"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Aligned Translations for Digital Scholarly Editions, Roma, Italy]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mapping Literary Space: A Social Network from the Timeline of Cultural Events</title><link href="https://mary-lev.github.io/blog/2024/dh2024-mapping-literary-space/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mapping Literary Space: A Social Network from the Timeline of Cultural Events"/><published>2024-08-06T09:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-06T09:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mary-lev.github.io/blog/2024/dh2024-mapping-literary-space</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mary-lev.github.io/blog/2024/dh2024-mapping-literary-space/"><![CDATA[<p>I presented my research on literary communities at the ADHO Digital Humanities Conference 2024 at George Mason University in Washington, DC. The presentation focused on mapping the social literary network in Saint Petersburg from 1999 to 2019 using social network analysis within the digital humanities framework.</p> <h2 id="research-overview">Research Overview</h2> <p>This study analyzes the cultural landscape of Saint Petersburg through the lens of social network analysis, examining how literary events and cultural activities create connections between writers, critics, and cultural institutions over two decades.</p> <h2 id="methodology">Methodology</h2> <p>The research is based on data extracted from SPbLitGuide newsletters, which documented literary events in Saint Petersburg from 1999 to 2019. Using network analysis techniques, I mapped the relationships between:</p> <ul> <li>Literary venues and institutions</li> <li>Authors and their collaborative networks</li> <li>Cultural events and their participants</li> <li>Temporal patterns in literary community formation</li> </ul> <h2 id="key-findings">Key Findings</h2> <p>The analysis revealed distinct patterns in how Saint Petersburg’s literary community evolved over the studied period, highlighting the role of specific venues, events, and individuals in shaping the city’s cultural landscape.</p> <h2 id="publication">Publication</h2> <p>The full abstract is available in the DH2024 Book of Abstracts: <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13761079">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13761079</a></p> <p>The underlying dataset is published on Zenodo: <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.10086515">Literary Events in Saint Petersburg (1999-2019)</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="conferences"/><category term="digital-humanities"/><category term="social-network-analysis"/><category term="digital-humanities"/><category term="literary-studies"/><category term="Saint-Petersburg"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[ADHO Digital Humanities Conference 2024, George Mason University, Washington, DC]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Handwritten text recongition slides</title><link href="https://mary-lev.github.io/blog/2024/handwrittten-text-recognition/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Handwritten text recongition slides"/><published>2024-04-30T13:56:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-30T13:56:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mary-lev.github.io/blog/2024/handwrittten-text-recognition</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mary-lev.github.io/blog/2024/handwrittten-text-recognition/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/mary-lev/mary-lev.github.io/master/assets/img/HTR.jpg" alt="Handwritten Text Recognition"/></p> <p>I recently presented at the University of Bologna’s seminar on “Machine Learning for Art and Humanities.” My presentation focused on handwritten text recognition (HTR), going over the HTR pipeline and looking at what’s currently being done in this area.</p> <p>Here are <a href="https://colab.research.google.com/drive/1aEcRFIMhzlfjy3Yq-o9tc-Gi-IPLwHsK?usp=sharing">two main HTR pipeline steps simplified with Google Colab</a>, <a href="https://github.com/mary-lev/HTR_demo">some data</a> and <a href="https://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/handwritten-text-recognition-for-manuscripts-and-early-printed-texts/267679039">the slides</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="ML,"/><category term="talks"/><category term="HTR,"/><category term="ATR,"/><category term="transformers,"/><category term="YOLO,"/><category term="TrOCR,"/><category term="manuscripts"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[HTR presentation]]></summary></entry></feed>